A Guide to the M. Rosaria Piomelli Architectural Papers, 1960-1997
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
M. Rosaria Piomelli Architectural Papers, 1960-1997
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1995-007
2 boxes, 4 oversize folders; 4.0 cu. ft.
The M. Rosaria Piomelli Architectural Papers consist of architectural drawings, correspondence, photographs, newspaper clippings, and files that chonicle the life and career of architect M. Rosaria Piomelli.
M. Rosaria Piomelli
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The M. Rosaria Piomelli Architectural Papers were donated to Special Collections in April 1995.
Biographical Information
M. Rosaria Piomelli (born Agrisano) was born in Naples, Italy, on October 24, 1937. She was educated at the Instituto d'Arte (1954, Bachelor of Arts) and Accedemia d'Arte (Master of Arts, 1955) of Naples, and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (1960, Bachelor of Architecture). Through the 1960s and 1970s she worked at various architects offices in Italy, New York, and the Netherlands, including I. M. Pei and Partners from 1971 to 1974 as a project architect. In 1974 she opened her own office in New York City.
From 1971 to 1976 Piomelli taught at the City College of New York School of Architecture as Adjunct Associate Professor, and from 1974 to 1979 taught at the Pratt Institute, where she served as Chair of the Faculty from 1976 to 1979. In 1979 she returned to CCNY as a Distinguished Professor, and was appointed Dean of the CCNY School of Architecture in 1980, becoming the first woman to hold a deanship of any school of architecture in the United States. She served in this position until 1983. In 1984 she was Visiting Distinguished Professor at the University of California at Berkeley, and from 1985 to the present she has had the position of full Professor at CCNY.
Piomelli has spent much of her career promoting the work of women in architecture. In 1974, as director the Equal Opportunity Committee for the American Institute of Architects, she organized an exhibit of women architects' work. This exhibit generated a great amount of interest in the standing of women in the profession. She served as a member of the Board of Advisors for the International Archive of Women in Architecture from 1985 to 1995.
Piomelli earned her professional licensure when she became a registered architect of New York State in 1969. She became a member of the American Institute of Architects in 1970 and served on various AIA committees throughout the 1970s, including Commisioner of the Schools of Architecture Committee of the New York City chapter from 1977 to 1979, and Director of the New York City Executive Committee from 1977 to 1979.
Publications by Piomelli include "Canary Wharf: London in the Third Millenium" in the March 1991 issue of Zodiac and as translator (from English to Italian) for Jan Gehl's Vitta in Citta (1992). Publications about Piomelli include information about her work in Susana Torre's Women in American Architecture (1977) and Insegnare L'Architettura, by M. Vegeto (1994).
Scope and Content
The papers consist of architectural drawings, correspondence, photographs, newspaper clippings, and files that chonicle the life and career of architect M. Rosaria Piomelli. The materials particularly focus on her architectural projects, mostly in the New York City area, and her tenure as head of the School of Architecture at the City College of New York from 1980 to 1983. Some of the literature and correspondence is in Italian.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by subject.
Contents List
- Curriculum vitae, 1960. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Correspondence relating to Artists Housing Coalition, Curriculum Vitae (c. 1978), artist's certification, Who's Who of American Women, AIA's exhibit on women in architecture, research proposals, tenure for Susana Torre, recommendation requests, curriculum vitae for various people, photocopies of articles, design reviews of several projects. Includes post cards and photographs. Many items in Italian, 1963-1990. (Box-folder 1:2)
- Oberlin College Library (Oberlin, OH). Items related to the Seeley G. Mudd Learning Center [Library]. Includes numerous photographs of interior views, exterior views, and drawings. This is work that Piomelli did in the office of Warner, Burns, Toan & Lunde, Architects, of New York City, 1966-1975. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Photographs of work Piomelli did in the office of E.F. Groosman in the Netherlands, 1968. (Box-folder 1:4)
- Photograph of Piomelli, 1970. (Box-folder 1:5)
- St. George Place, Staten Island, NY (designed by I.M. Pei). Piomelli was project architect, 1972. (Box-folder 1:6)
- St. George Place, Staten Island, NY. Photographs, preliminary outline specifications, 1973. (Box-folder 1:7)
- Raffle International Centre, Singapore. I.M. Pei & Partners, Architects. Twenty-one different floor plans and elevations of the structure, August 9, 1974, 1974. (Box-folder 1:8)
- "Women in Architecture, from This to This" by P.D. Benson. The Australian Women's Weekly, July 31, 1974. About an AIA exhibit mounted by Piomelli at the AIA building in New York City, 1974. (Box-folder 1:9)
- Curriculum vitae, 1976. (Box-folder 1:10)
- Correspondence relating, but not limited, to faculty review, job notices, the Chancellor Distinguished Lectureship at the U niversity of California at Berkeley, list of projects undertaken in private pr actice, the Deanship of School of Architecture, conference participation, consulting work for hotel design for JFK airport, requests for letters of recommendations, professional organizations, personal topics, Brooklyn Museum Master Plan Design Competition, grants, and photocopies of newspaper and magazine articles. Some photographs and post cards. Some correspondence in Italian, 1977-1997. (Box-folder 1:11)
- Piomelli as Dean of City College of CUNY, tenure decisions, curriculum vitae and biographical information, 1980-1984. (Box-folder 1:12-13)
- Issue of Interni 315 LA Rivistia dell'Arredamenta with article by Piomelli, "L'Architetto Ferma Il Loft," 1981. (Box-folder 1:14)
- Interiors, June 1982 issue. Article about Piomelli, "Piomelli of City College: Top Teacher Profile," by Maeve Slavin, 1982. (Box-folder 1:15)
- "Four on the Jury" in Interiors about the jury for the Third Annual Interiors Awards, of which Piomelli was a member, 1982. (Box-folder 1:16)
- Schiff residence (Montauk, NY), contracts with others, 1982-1983. (Box-folder 1:17)
- Materials related to the City College of the City University of New York tenure decision for Piomelli, 1982-1984. (Box-folder 1:18)
- Schiff apartment (New York, NY), general files about renovation, 1983. (Box-folder 1:19)
- Schiff residence (Montauk, NY), slides and photographs, mostly of model, 1983. (Box-folder 1:20)
- Curriculum vitae with examples of professional work, teaching, and research activities, 1983. (Box-folder 1:21)
- Cerami residence (Shelter Island, NY), model slides and preliminary sketches, 1983. (Box-folder 1:22)
- Schiff residence (Montauk, NY), correspondence, 1983-1984. (Box-folder 1:23)
- Schiff residence (Montauk, NY), details, and windows and doors, 1983-1984. (Box-folder 1:24)
- Editorial Advisory Board of Interiors magazine, 1983-1984. (Box-folder 1:25)
- Schiff residence (Montauk, NY), zoning and building permit, 1983-1987. (Box-folder 1:26)
- Pierson School (Tarrytown, NY) conversion to apartments. Materials include building permit, newspaper article about school, photographs, and literature about building plans, 1984. (Box-folder 1:27)
- Cerami residence (Shelter Island, NY), outline specifications, estimates, and energy conservation data, 1984. (Box-folder 1:28)
- Cerami residence (Shelter Island, NY), outline specifications, 1984-1985. (Box-folder 1:29)
- Cerami residence (Shelter Island, NY), specifications, invoices, blueprints, notes, and contracts, 1985. (Box-folder 1:30)
- Curriculum vitaes, 1985-1995. (Box-folder 1:31)
- Issue of the Italian magazine Costruire (No. 73, May 1989), with article, "Non Si Studia Si Abita" about Piomelli's work on the Pierson School apartments, 1989. (Box-folder 1:32)
- "Interview with Rosaria Piomelli," transcript of interview. Interview focuses on the problems women face in academia, and recounts times Piomelli had faced discrimination when she taught at CCNY. Done for the American Collegiate Schools of Architecture Task Force on the Status of Women in Architecture Schools, 1990. (Box-folder 1:33)
- Photographs of interior of the Tauber residence, 1991. (Box-folder 1:34)
- IAWA Newsletter, Fall 1995 issue, with an article by Piomelli, "Looking Back from the 10th Anniversary of the IAWA", 1995. (Box-folder 1:35)
- Scrapbook of project drawings, photographs, and plans, n.d. (Box-folder 1:36-37)
- List of published work by Piomelli, n.d. (Box-folder 1:38)
- Brown University Science Library, 1965-1973. (Box-folder 2:1)
- Pages from the May 18, 1974, New York Times with an article, "Women Architects Building Influence in a Profession That is 98.8% Male," by P. Goldberger which highlights Piomelli, 1974. (Box-folder 2:2)
- Poster calling for submissions to the "Women in Architecture" exhibit organized by Piomelli, 1974?. (Box-folder 2:3)
- Poster advertising the "Women in Architecture" exhibit organized by Piomelli, 1974. (Box-folder 2:4)
- April 11, 1974, issue of Chelsea Clinton News with article by C. Meinhardt, "A Male-dominating Field Gives Way to Women" that features Piomelli and the women in architecture exhibit she organized, 1974. (Box-folder 2:5)
- Page from the July 6, 1980, issue of the New York Times with article "A Female Dean of Architecture Who has Designs on the Future," by N. Robertson, featuring Piomelli, 1980. (Box-folder 2:6)
- September 3, 1980, issue of The Campus (an undergraduate newspaper of the City College of New York) with an article about Piomelli being named the School of Architecture and Urban Studies first woman dean, 1980. (Box-folder 2:7)
- Pierson School (Tarrytown, NY), mock-up for brochure about renovation, 1984-1986?. (Box-folder 2:8)
- Pages from the Gannett Westchester Newpapers, April 22, 1985, issue with article, "Pierson School Meeting Causes Flap Among Board Members," about the building's development (Piomelli owned and renovated the building), 1985. (Box-folder 2:9)
- Pierson School (Tarrytown, NY) drawings, details and tracings, 1986. (Box-folder 2:10)
- Descriptions of three designs in which Piomelli served as project director Oberlin College Library (Warner, Burns, Toan & Lunde, Architects), Brown University Science Library (Warner, Burns, Toan & Lunde, Architects), St. George Place (I.M. Pei & Partners), n.d. (Box-folder 2:11)
- Little Italy Risorgimento, 100 Unit Housing and Public School by Michael Muroff, Rosaria Piomelli, Pratt Institute. Four sheets of floorplans and elevations, n.d. (Box-folder 2:12)
- Tauber Apartment, drawings and photographs, n.d. (Box-folder 2:13)
- Pierson School (Tarrytown, NY) renovation drawings, 1983-1986, n.d. (Oversize 1)
  - Emergency lights (4 drawings, 1st-4th floors).
  - Floor plans (15 drawings, all floors and mezzanine).
  - Site utilities (1 drawing, 3 copies).
  - Typical details, general notes, column schedule, each floor and mezzanine, roof (1 drawing).
  - Site development plan (4 copies).
  - Planting plan.
- Red Hook Development (New York, NY). Piomelli listed among contributing architects, 1980-1991, n.d. (Oversize 2)
  - Sectional Map of New York, NY, Dept. of City Planning.
  - "Reclaiming the City's Edge, Comprehensive Waterfront Plan," New York City Dept. of City Planning. Map of New York City.
  - General site plan, includes a copy with views from surrounding streets.
  - Elevation of the Gateway from the waterfront/prespective sketch/perspective sketch from waterfront: functional plan (2 copies), proposed plan (2 copies), satellite photograph, functional plan.
- Miscellaneous projects, 1977-1991, n.d. (Oversize 3)
  - Five panels of architectural drawings for a competition to redesign Octagon Park, Washington, D.C.
  - Schiff Apartment (one drawing).
  - Schiff House, Montauk, NY (nine drawings): site plan, 1st and 2nd floor plan, finish & door schedule, floor plans & sections, exterior elevations, interior elevations, foundation & framing plans, framing sections, heating & ventilation system, electrical.
  - Cerami House (12 drawings): site plan & plumbing diagram, floor plans, roof plan & schedules, elevations, bath & kitchen elevations, structural plans (2 sheets), construction details, foundation drawings, floor plans--electrical, floor plans--mechanical, wall section, kitchen flooring & steps details.
  - Academy Hill Development (Hudson, NY): site plan, unit plan, typical cluster plans, section, elevation.
  - Buckle My Shoe (New York, NY): cellar floor plans, first floor plan, general notes.
  - Artist Living-Work Quarters (New York, NY): conversion plan.
  - Vyse Avenue Rehabiliation (Bronx, NY): ground floor plan, floor plan, 2, 3, 4 (typical), cellar floor plan.
  - Poster, Washington University School of Architecture, lecture series. Piomelli listed among speakers.
- "Women in Architecture, An Exhibition of Work by Women": 2 sheets. Original drawings for exhibition poster (Rolled), n.d. (Oversize 4)